Welcome back to the Wheel of Life
Home Retreat.
I would like to thank Stanley again for the translation.
Thank you for being in America and translating.
We're in lesson 21 and
it's called "Seeing Prison as Prison."  The
picture shows a prison.
We used to have a very intensive program of training lama rim in prisons.
And it helped the prisoners a lot,
and the government thanked us because the prisoners started getting into fights less.
The picture you see here is perfect for prison, because
prison is really depressing.
When we study the Wheel of Life in the monastery,
we study it from a set of books called sur kel (ZUR BKOL).
There is a tradition of taking about five different subjects
and squeezing specific topics out of the larger books, much like
you would squeeze medicine out of herbs.
And for our computer project to preserve ancient books,
this was the first book we printed,
and it was called sur kel (ZUR BKOL), five books
extracted from the big books.
And you will be interested to know,
and we have been studying it for 2-3 months,
that the entire teaching of the "Wheel of Life",
as it is taught in the monastery,
all of it comes from one verse from Maitreya.
More precisely, from one verse, not a stanza.
And I think you have heard this verse from me before,
the ne seng khe nam gying pei (DE NAS SENG GE RNAM BSGYINGS PA'I)
ting nge jing la nyom shuk ne (TING NGE 'DZIN LA SNYOMS ZHUGS NAS,)
ten ching drill jung luk thun thang luk mi thun la tok par che (RTEN CING 'BREL 'BYUNG LUGS MTHUN DANG,, LUGS MI MTHUN LA RTOG PAR BYED)
This teaches both the "Lion Dance"
and the "Wheel of Life".
And the part I want to talk about today
is the final part.
It says ten ching drill jung luk thun thang luk mi thun (RTEN CING 'BREL 'BYUNG LUGS MTHUN DANG LUGS MI MTHUN) luk thun thang luk
mi thun (LUGS MTHUN DANG,,LUGS MI MTHUN) luk thun
(LUGS MTHUN) means one causes two, two causes three, three causes four, etc.
The wife in the kitchen says: “I didn’t do anything, and he yelled at me,”
this is link number one.
Then she screams back.
This is luk thun (LUGS MTHUN), which means the usual order of things
Then luk thun (LUGS MTHUN), which is sometimes called luk dok (LUGS LDOG)
This means to turn the wheel back,
to stop the wheel.
And you tend to think, oh, it must be, since it's spoken backwards,
It must go from the twelfth, to the eleventh, to the tenth...
First I die,
then I grow old, then I'm born, then my karma gains weight,
then I weaponize karma,
I mean, you can have such strange thoughts.
But here in the lam rim it is described what it actually means to "spin the wheel back"
the tak luk dok tu khok nyu pey lam shik nyam su len na (DE DAG LUGS LDOG TU 'GOG NUS PA'I LAM ZHIG NYAMS SU LEN NA)
we follow the Tibetan;
the tak luk dok tu khok nyu pey lam shik nyam su len na (DE DAG LUGS LDOG TU 'GOG NUS PA'I LAM ZHIG NYAMS SU LEN NA),
if you embark on a path
that will give you the opportunity
to stop the Wheel of Life by turning it back.
What does it mean to turn the Wheel of Life back, to stop the Wheel of Life?
mar rik pa khak pe thu chye khak (MA RIG PA 'GAG PAS 'DU BYED 'GAGS)
If you stop misunderstanding, then you stop karma.
Let's apply this to the kitchen,
this is where you should apply all your Dharma.
If you can't apply it in the kitchen, it's not Dharma.
Then if it is Dharma, you can apply it in the kitchen.  Something like that.  There
shouldn't be anything in the 300,000 books on Buddhism that we have that you couldn't find in your kitchen.
And if something good or bad happens in the kitchen, it should be described in ancient books.
Because ancient books were written for the kitchen.
ma rik pa khak ne thu chiye khak (MA RIG PA 'GAG PAS 'DU BYED 'GAGS)
means if she can stop the
misunderstanding regarding her husband,
if she doesn't say, "I don't know why he yelled at me,"
but says, "Ah, I know why he yelled at me!
I yelled at my kids last week."
She just reversed the first link.
She just blocked the first link.
If you block this "I didn't do anything,"
then automatically you won't get to the second link.
"I'm not clueless, you're clueless."
Okay.
So if you stop the first link, then the second link will never come.
That's how we stop the Wheel of Life.
Don't forget that the Wheel of Life is kind of a bad name, a misnomer.
It's not really the Wheel of Life.
I mean, Buddha has a life too.
It means the wheel of bad life and the life  full of suffering.
If you stop link #1, you stop link #2.
Therefore, you stop all links, including aging and dying. All the pain in your life will
be stopped.
And don't think that the Wheel of Life means that if you get off the Wheel of Life, you have to die or disappear.
In the Wheel of Life, for example, in the painting,
Buddha is outside the wheel,
and he points to the moon,
which represents nirvana.
Okay, let's get back to the text.
nyon mong duk ngel gyi ten drel sum thu thu te (MDOR BSDU NA, RTEN 'BREL YAN LAG BCU GNYIS LAS DANG NYON MONGS SDUG BSNGAL GYI RTEN 'BREL GSUM DU 'DU STE)
tor du na (MDOR BSDU NA) means, let's summarize
You can take all 12 links
And to summarize, we can divide them a little differently than we did before.
We can divide them into number 1 - karma
number 2 - negative thoughts
and number 3 pain.
Okay, you can divide them into these three.
mar rik pa thang se pa len pa sum nyon mong (MA RIG PA DANG, SRED PA, LEN PA GSUM NYON MONGS)
The three links are negative emotions;
This is the misunderstanding of your husband,
And then se pa (SRED PA) we  They said this is a negative coffee meditation. Do
you regret yelling at your husband? No.
Then LEN PA, this is like an advanced negative coffee meditation.
I don't believe there is any connection between yelling at my children and my husband yelling at me.
So, these are all three negative thoughts.
Link number 2 and link number 10,
these two are karma,
but different stages of karma.
Number 2 is fresh karma, like a watermelon just planted.
Yes, and number 10 is ripe karma, the seeds are swollen and ready.
Yes, okay, translate that while I drink my coffee.
Then, he says a strange thing;
LHAG MA BDUN NI SDUG BSNGAL,
and the other seven,  they are suffering.
And then he quotes lu drup (KLU SGRUB),
Arya Nagarjuna.
And this is by the way the same text on the essence of dependent origination
that we had before. It's very short. One or two pages.
So let's follow the Tibetan text because there are two interesting points here;
thang po gye pa gu nyon mong (DANG PO BRGYAD PA DGU NYON MONGS)
The first, eighth and nine
are negative thoughts,
the first, eighth and nine.
See,
he doesn't say the ninth.
He says nine, Nagarjuna.
Why didn't he say the ninth and just said nine?
Because, this is poetry, and he didn't have room to write the "-th".
So you won't get confused.
You should hear pa gu pa (PA, DGU PA).
Okay, now it should be clear, number 1, number 8, number 9, these three are negative emotions.
nye pa chu pa le yin  te (GNYIS PA BCU PA LAS YIN TE)
number 2 and number 10, these are the two karmas, these two are karmas.
hlak ma dun ni (LHAG MA BDUN NI)
now the remaining 7, the remaining 7,
duk ngel yin (SDUG BSNGAL YIN) - these are suffering.
Now, I always like to go back to the original text
at any point, this is the Mixed Nuts rule.
Whenever there is a quote in the book,
our translation team's rule is Mixed Nuts,
we are all the
reincarnations of Master Xuanzang's (XUANGZANG) students in the
Wild Goose Pagoda Tower during the time of Tangchao (TANGCHAO).
We have a rule,
if there is a quote, go and check it and make sure it is correct.
So I checked it and then I told myself that it is correct.
Then I noticed that one word is different, the way
it is quoted in the lam  Rome, The
last line says LHAG MA BDUN NI,
which means the last, remaining seven,
they are suffering,
but it's a little uncomfortable, right? That is, the others must also be suffering, and the whole wheel is suffering.
The real ancient Tang Gyur (BSTANG 'GYUR) version of this verse
says LHAG MA BDUN YANG
not NI.
Okay, here, look here LHAG MA BDUN NI,
but it says LHAG MA BDUN YANG.
Which means the
remaining seven are also pain.
So, I think everyone who has listened to this lesson up to this point,
I can accept that three of them are negative emotions - number one, eight and nine.
I can understand that two of them are karma - number two and ten.
But why does he say and the remaining seven are suffering?
Why does he do this  says, aren't those first five suffering too?
And if you thought of that when you heard me say it the first time,
you were right.
Because the original verse said the last seven are suffering too.
So I did my third-grade drawing here;
I colored in around the first, eighth, and ninth links, which are the negative emotions.
Then in the next picture,
I colored in around numbers two and ten together.
And then in the next picture, I colored in around three through seven and eleven – twelfth, those seven.
And of course, by now you know that those two groups are kind of the same thing.
3, 4, 5, 6,
7, and 11 and 12.
They're almost the same thing.
Why?
Number 3, my consciousness goes into my mom,
link number 4, my body and my consciousness are inside my mom,
link number 5, my eyes and ears and nose and so on grow inside my  moms.
link number 6 - they come into contact with the outside world,
link number 7 - because of this contact, I have feelings, such as good feelings or bad feelings.
3, 4, 5, 6, 7
but they are the same as 11 and 12.
11 and 12 together are one whole human life.
I am born, I grow old, and I die.
diy tsik kang thang po (DI'I TSIG RKANG DANG PO)
so, these three pictures I made for you.
diy tsik kang thang poy the sum kun long thang (DI'I TSIG RKANG DANG PO'I DE GSUM KUN SLONG DANG)
He said something interesting
you can remember the first line of the verse, well
where Nagarjuna says that the first, and the eighth, and the ninth, they are negative emotions.
You can  think of them as the process of motivation to do something bad.
Then, you can remember the next stanza,
this next stanza says that number 2 and number 10 are karma.
If you think about it,
number 2 and number 10,
they are karma expressed by you doing something or saying something.
Where is the mental karma?
He already talked about that in the first group. The
first group, those three mental obscurations are mental karma.
What does link number 1 and link number 2 mean?
Number 2, he says here,
must refer to the things you say and the things you do because of your bad motivation.
Why link 2, the potter, did he leave out the karma of thinking?
Because that was already in the wrong understanding.
This is the karma of the mind.
Okay,
tsig kang sum pei the nam long cho yin (TSIG RKANG GSUM PA'I DE  RNAMS LONGS SPYOD YIN)
Then, in the third line here, which says the other seven are suffering,
these links are just like what objects in your life that you cognize.
If you reflect
on these 12 links;
what order they go in and how you stop them.
Then indeed, you automatically do the meditation on the pain of life.
And then automatically there will be a shift in your heart.
You will begin to understand, “Oh my god, I’m like a prisoner in this wheel,
this world is a prison.”
My life is a prison.
And I’m doomed in this prison.
My whole life I’ve been in prison. The
only  The way to escape this prison is to die.
And that's not a metaphor—that's reality.
No matter how rich you are,
no matter how young you are,
it doesn't matter,
you're still locked in the prison of death.
A. No. 1, you'd have to be crazy to think that all the people before you died, but you're not going to die.
Then, if someone told you, you know, there's a pretty simple way to stop this problem,
then I think you'd have to be crazy not to at least listen to them.
So the whole idea—"my life is like a prison,"
no matter what happens in my life, good or bad,
I'm going to lose everything, even my life.
Then, finally, you have this idea: "Oh, maybe there's a way I can get out."
I mean, "I don't want to die,
but I would like to change my life and make it like heaven.
I would like that.
Then he says nge jung yin (NGES 'BYUNG YIN)
this is renunciation.
In English, the word renunciation, especially by waiters and restaurateurs, was never used.
Even in the ancient Christian tradition, where this word came from,
it means that I will stay in the monastery, I will eat simple food, I will have a simple bed, something like that.
But the word in Buddhism, the original word is nge jung (NGES ' BYUNG)
it feels different and has a different meaning.
Of course, all of you who have studied the ACI courses know that this is the first of the three main paths,
and it is very simple to explain -
it simply means, I want to get out of here!
This does not mean what the Christian word "renunciation" means.  This is not what is meant.
This doesn't mean I'm going to avoid fine dining, or not go on vacation, or not watch movies.
In Buddhism, nge jung (NGES ' BYUNG) means I definitely want to get out of here.
So your life from the moment you are born
, from the minute you are born until the minute you die, it is
all exactly the same as a prison.
When you say, "This guy is rich," you simply mean that this guy has more money in his prison cell,
which is the same cell I am in.
Or "that movie star is very beautiful,"
but that just means she's in the same prison cell as me and she's going to lose all her beauty too.
I don't see that the word "renunciation" means a gloomy person who is ordained to the priesthood.
In many religious traditions, including Buddhism,
the image of renunciation in your mind
is of a monk or nun who is not particularly happy.
They won't eat donuts because they taste good.
You don't think about anyone happy.
But what we were talking about today is
if you achieve true renunciation
it's something like Steve Jobs or something like that.
It means you're really excited about a new idea, that's all.
It's like a new vision, what's that guy's name, Elon Musk
Yeah, let's make a new spaceship,
let's make a new kind of car.
And renunciation should be exactly like this
Yes, that's right, let's get out of this shitty world, let's make a cool world.
Yes, we could do that.
It's like... I don't know...
Elon Musk doesn't want to drive a car that pollutes the entire planet,
he has some kind of positive, happy, cool vision.
Yeah, let's get rid of these stinking cars,
everyone will get a Tesla, and then the whole world will be clean.
This is what renunciation should taste like.
I want a cool world, I don't want this stupid world.
Grow old,
shrivel up like an old monkey,
then lose teeth, then die, you know.
This is not cool
I want something cool.
Okay, so experience this feeling about renunciation.
I don't know, but you probably felt that
here the lamrim
shifts away
from explaining the problem.
And you might have felt something like this
Elon Musk vibe of
"Oh, we'll have a solution soon..."
and let's get to the solution in the next video.
See you!